<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Viz on Samples of Thoughts</title>
    <link>/tags/data-viz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Viz on Samples of Thoughts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Corrie Bartelheimer {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data-viz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Animated Facebook Messages</title>
      <link>/2020/animated-facebook-messages/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/animated-facebook-messages/</guid>
      <description>I recently downloaded my own Facebook data and wanted to find out what kind of data gems I could find. There are some clear advantages when analyzing your own data, foremost, you’re the expert and know the “ground truth” behind the data. That said, there can still be big surprises!
In my case, the most interesting parts of the analysis could be boiled down in two graphics. Since there’s also a time factor in the data, I thought this is a good opportunity to learn about animated plots and indeed, it works quite beautifully with the two plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visa Costs meet Data Viz</title>
      <link>/2020/visa-costs-data-viz/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/visa-costs-data-viz/</guid>
      <description>I recently stumbled across this data set about visa costs. It is a collection of visa costs for all countries for different kind of visas (tourist, business, work, transit, and some other visas). Each row corresponds to visa relations between a source country (the country applying for the visa) and a target country (the country issuing the visa) together with the cost for the different visa types.
Since I had a bit of free time on my hand, I decided to do some “plotcrastinating”, play around with the data and try out some new visualizations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>