<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Samples of Thoughts</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Samples of Thoughts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Corrie Bartelheimer {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Animated Facebook Messages</title>
      <link>/2020/animated-facebook-messages/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/animated-facebook-messages/</guid>
      <description>I recently downloaded my own Facebook data and wanted to find out what kind of data gems I could find. There are some clear advantages when analyzing your own data, foremost, you’re the expert and know the “ground truth” behind the data. That said, there can still be big surprises!
In my case, the most interesting parts of the analysis could be boiled down in two graphics. Since there’s also a time factor in the data, I thought this is a good opportunity to learn about animated plots and indeed, it works quite beautifully with the two plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI Guild Podcast: Data Science Interviews</title>
      <link>/2020/ai-guild-podcast-data-science-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/ai-guild-podcast-data-science-interviews/</guid>
      <description>On turning the tables during job interviews as you experience grows Some time ago, I sat down with Leyla from the AI Guild to talk about my own Data Science path but also my experience in job interviews for data positions. Recently, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been interviewing for positions, I wondered how to find out some more sensitive topics. How is the company keeping it with diversity? Is diversity important for them and do they take active measures to increase e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visa Costs meet Data Viz</title>
      <link>/2020/visa-costs-data-viz/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/visa-costs-data-viz/</guid>
      <description>I recently stumbled across this data set about visa costs. It is a collection of visa costs for all countries for different kind of visas (tourist, business, work, transit, and some other visas). Each row corresponds to visa relations between a source country (the country applying for the visa) and a target country (the country issuing the visa) together with the cost for the different visa types.
Since I had a bit of free time on my hand, I decided to do some “plotcrastinating”, play around with the data and try out some new visualizations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting Disinformation with tidygraph</title>
      <link>/2020/connecting-disinformation-with-tidygraph/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/connecting-disinformation-with-tidygraph/</guid>
      <description>I recently participated in a hackathon organised by EU’s anti-disinformation task force where they gave us access to their data base. The data base consists of all disinformation cases the group has collected since it started in 2015. Their data can also be browsed online on their web page www.euvsdisinfo.eu. The data contains more than 7000 cases of disinformation, mostly news articles and videos, that were collected and debunked by the EUvsDisinfo project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House-Cleaning: Getting rid of outliers II</title>
      <link>/2020/outlier-handling-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/outlier-handling-two/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we tried to clean rental offerings of outliers. We first just had a look at our data and tried to clean by simply using threshold derived from our own knowledge about flats with minor success. We got slightly better results by using the IQR rule and learned two things: First, the IQR rule works better if our data is normally distributed and, if it’s not, transforming it can work wonders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House-Cleaning: Getting rid of outliers I</title>
      <link>/2020/outlier-handling-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/outlier-handling-one/</guid>
      <description>Working with real-world data presents many challenges that sanitized text book data doesn’t have. One of them is how to handle outlier. Outliers are defined as points that differ significantly from other data points and they are especially common in data obtained through manual input processes. For example, on an online listing site, someone might accidentally pressed the zero-key a bit too often and suddenly the small rental flat is as expensive as a palace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Time: Predictive Analytics World 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/conference-time-predictive-analytics-world-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/conference-time-predictive-analytics-world-2019/</guid>
      <description>In the last two years, I pretty much only went to very technical conferences, such as the PyData Berlin, the PyCon or the SatRday. They&amp;rsquo;re all great conferences, organized by awesome people and I will definitely go again but this fall I decided to try out a new conference and check out the Predictive Analytics World in Berlin. First, because it&amp;rsquo;s always good to try out new things and also because in the last months I was wondering a lot how data teams can be made more useful, somehow more aligned with the business challenges, which frankly isn&amp;rsquo;t talked much in Python talks about how to deploy machine learning models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible (Data) Science with Docker and R</title>
      <link>/2019/reproducible-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/reproducible-data-science/</guid>
      <description>In my data team at work, we’ve been using Docker for a while now. At least, the engineers in our team have been using it, we data scientists have been very reluctant to pick it up so far. Why bother with a new tool (that seems complicated) when you don’t see the reason, right?
Until I was about to hold my Houseprice Talk again and wanted to make some small changes to my xaringan slides and nothing worked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the European Election: The Candidates</title>
      <link>/2019/european-election-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/european-election-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>The European Election is coming up and for the first time, I have the impression this election is actually talked about and might have an impact. I don’t remember people caring that much about European Elections in the years before, but this, of course, could also just be because I got more interested in European politics. Unfortunately, European politics are complex and this is also mirrored in the quantity of parties that are up for vote in Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping the web or how to find a flat</title>
      <link>/2018/scraping-the-web-or-how-to-find-a-flat/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/scraping-the-web-or-how-to-find-a-flat/</guid>
      <description>Berlin is a great city that used to have the reputation of affordable rents. While for sure other cities are still much more expensive, the rents in Berlin have risen considerably. Or so says everyone of my friends and my colleagues and so does it feel looking at renting listings. I decided to have a look myself at the data to find out if there’s still a secret neighborhood in Berlin resisting the raising prices and who knows, maybe the data can even tell us if the neighborhood Wedding is indeed “coming”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make a website using blogdown and github</title>
      <link>/2018/how-to-make-a-website-using-blogdown-and-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/how-to-make-a-website-using-blogdown-and-github/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I will describe how to build your own webpage (more specific, a blog) using blogdown and have it hosted on your github.
 Set up your github repo so it can serve as a web page Build your website using blogdown  Set up Github Let’s start with setting up your github. This is actually super simple, you only need to create a new repository with the name &amp;lt;yourusername&amp;gt;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my blog!</title>
      <link>/2018/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Hello World! I’m Corrie and this is my blog where I plan to occasionally write about interesting topics. Interesting topics is of course entirely subjective and for me, machine learning, statistics (in particular the Bayesian flavor), and data science sound very exciting, so most of my posts will touch any of these topics. As a Mathematician by training, I spent quite some time during my studies with differential geometry, topology, and number theory (knots and prime numbers are cool!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>